A Finding Aid to the John Henry Bradley Storrs Papers, 1790-2007, bulk 1900-1956, in the Archives of American Art AAA.storjohn
Archives of American Art
John Henry Bradley Storrs papers
bulk 1900-1956
1790-2007
AAA.storjohn
Archives of American Art
19.8 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor, painter, and printmaker John Henry Bradley Storrs measure 19.8 linear feet and date from 1790-2007, with the bulk of the papers dating from 1900 to 1956. The collection contains biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, forty-eight diaries of John Storrs, a few diaries of other family members, additional writings, printed material, photographs of Storrs and his family and friends, artwork, scrapbooks, estate records, and video recordings. Correspondence includes that of John Storrs, Marguerite Storrs, and the Storrs family.
Storrs, John Henry Bradley
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The John Henry Bradley Storrs papers were donated in several installments from 1979 to 1987 by Storrs' daughter, Monique Storrs Booz, and her daughter, Michelle Storrs Booz. A portion of these papers were loaned for microfilming in 1977 and subsequently donated in 1980. Additional papers were donated by Michelle Storrs Booz in 2011.
Separated Materials note
The Booz family also loaned approximately 1,000 drawings by John Storrs and select family photographs for microfilming. Loaned material is available for viewing on reel 1555, but is not described in this container listing of this finding aid.
Related Archival Materials note
Also available at the Archives of American Art is the Noel Frackman research material on John Henry Bradley Storrs, 1972-2003. In addition, Archives of American Art microfilm reels 1463 and ND/S-1 contain the John Henry Bradley Storrs scrapbook and studio book, 1909-1972.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This site provides access to the papers of John Henry Bradley Storrs in the Archives of American Art that were digitized in 2006, and total 27498 images.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Biographical/Historical note
John Henry Bradley Storrs (1885-1956) worked primarily in Chicago, Illinois, and Mer, France, as a sculptor, painter, and printmaker.
John Storrs was born in 1885 in Chicago, Illinois, to David William Storrs, an architect, and Hannah Bradley Storrs. Upon completing his schooling in 1905 he went to Berlin with the intention of studying music, but instead chose to study sculpture with the Arthur Bock in Hamburg, Germany. He also spent time in Paris and traveled throughout Europe, Turkey, and Egypt, returning to the US in late 1907. Storrs took night classes at the Art Institute of Chicago, followed by periods of study at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, with Bela Pratt, and at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts with Charles Grafly. In 1912 he returned to Paris where he studied at the Académie Julian and with the famous sculptor Auguste Rodin. During this period his work was greatly influenced by cubism and futurism. In 1914 he married French writer Marguerite Deville-Chabrol. After briefly returning to the US to exhibit his work, Storrs worked at a hospital in Paris throughout World War I and in 1918 his daughter Monique was born. He and his family settled in Mer, France, at the Chateau de Chantecaille in 1921.
The following two decades were very productive for Storrs and he frequently travelled between the US and France to exhibit and create work. He showed in many notable exhibits such as the Société Anonyme's International Exhibition of Modern Art in New York in 1926, and he completed several commissions such as a statue for the Chicago Board of Trade in 1929. During this time Storrs completely moved away from representational work and refined his non-objective, machine-like sculpture. Besides sculpture, he also produced many paintings, woodcuts, lithographs, and other works on paper. He created works for the Century of Progress International Exposition in 1933 and also worked for the Public Works of Art Project in 1934.
During World War II Storrs was twice arrested and imprisoned by the German occupation forces, once for six months from 1941 to 1942 and again in 1944 along with his daughter Monique who was part of the French Resistance. These events greatly impacted his health and he produced very little work in the late 1940s and 1950s. He continued to exhibit his work and was also president in 1954 of the Ecole de la Loire, a group of 75 artists working in the Loire Valley. John Storrs died in 1956.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor, painter, and printmaker John Henry Bradley Storrs measure 19.8 linear feet and date from 1790 to 2007, with the bulk of the papers dating from 1900 to 1956. The collection documents Storrs' career as an artist and his personal life through biographical material, correspondence with family, friends, and colleagues, personal business records, forty-eight diaries and other writings, printed material, photographs of Storrs and his family and friends, artwork, scrapbooks, estate records, and video recordings. There is also a substantial amount of Marguerite Storr's correspondence as well as scattered correspondence of other members of the Storr's family.
Biographical material consists of chronologies detailing the life of John Storrs, identification records, certificates, Storrs family documents, and records of John and Monique Storrs' French resistance activities during World War II.
Correspondence within this collection is divided into John Storrs Correspondence, Marguerite Storrs Correspondence, and Storrs Family Correspondence. The bulk of correspondence is John Storrs with friends, colleagues, art critics, patrons, art organizations and galleries. Correspondents of note include artists, architects, and writers such as Hendrick Andersen, Sherwood Anderson, Edward Bennett, George Biddle, Jerome Blum, Georges Braque, Louise Bryant, William Bullitt, Alexander Calder, Walter Cole, Paul Phillippe Cret, Katherine Dreier, Marcel Duchamp, Max Eastman, R. Buckminster Fuller, Marsden Hartley, Jane Heap, Jean Helion, Fernand Leger, Jacques Lipchitz, Man Ray, Charles Sheeler, Gertrude Stein, Joseph Stella, Maurice Sterne, Alfred Stieglitz, Leopold Survage, and William and Marguerite Zorach. There are also many letters to his wife Marguerite.
Marguerite Storrs' correspondence is with friends, family, colleagues, and others, including many letters to her husband. The letters are about general and family news, social activities and invitations, her work as a writer, and her husband's career. Storrs' family correspondence includes John and Marguerite's extensive correspondence with their daughter Monique as well as Monique's correspondence with others. Additional family correspondence is between John, his sister Mary ("Mae") and their parents David William and Hannah Storrs, much of it dating from 1900 to 1913.
Personal business records include address books, records regarding the sale and loan of Storrs' artwork, commission files regarding major public sculptures by Storrs, contracts, appraisals, financial records, and other documents regarding his professional activities. Of note are several files documenting Downtown Gallery's representation of Storrs' work during the 1960s, including correspondence between Edith Halpert and Monique Storrs. Various other documents include records of the Ecole de la Loire artists group (all in French.) Additionally there are records relating to Chateau de Chantecaille, an estate purchased by Storrs in the early 1920s as his primary residence and studio.
Forty-eight diaries contain scattered documentation of John Storrs' daily activities. Other writings by Storrs include four volumes of his memoirs that detail family history and his life from birth to 1906, notebooks, poetry, and personal accounts including the death of Auguste Rodin. Writings by others include poetry by Jessie Dismorr, essays by Zoltan Hecht and Maurice Raynal, and notebooks belonging to Storrs family members.
Printed material consists of books, art bulletins, brochures, invitations, announcements, and programs for art and social events. Also found are catalogs for exhibitions of Storrs' work and work by other artists; magazines, including a bound volume of the first ten issues of The Liberator; and clippings which include news about Storrs, his family, and friends.
Photographs depict John Storrs, his family, friends such as Arthur Bock and Gertrude Lambert, travels, and residences. Included are photographs of Storrs in his studio and in art classes. Also found are four photograph albums, primarily documenting his time in Europe from 1905 to 1907, exhibition photographs, and numerous photographs of his artwork.
Original artwork includes a portfolio of artwork created by Storrs as a youth, loose sketches, one sketchbook, 31 lithographs, and drawings for mural projects.
Four scrapbooks and a portfolio kept by John and Marguerite Storrs contain newspaper and magazine clippings of articles and illustrations as well as printed material from exhibitions, social events, and professional activities. Also found is a portfolio containing scattered items regarding the publication of Song of Myself with original wood engravings by John Storrs. One additional scrapbook was created by John Storrs around 1945 for his daughter, Monique Storrs, to document her service as a nurse in World War II.
This collection also includes records of John Storrs' estate immediately following his death in 1956, as well as records of several galleries that represented the estate in managing Storrs' artwork from the 1970s to 2002.
Three videocassettes, transferred from an unknown reel format, contain footage of Storrs' family life at Chantecaille and in Chicago, Illinois, in the 1930s.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 11 series.
Some box and folder numbers in the container listing intentionally display out of sequence. An accretion was added in 2012 and integrated into the intellectual order, but not into the physical container order. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1837, 1860-1984 (Box 1, 20, 25, OV 23; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1857-2007 (Box 1-7, 25; 5.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1790, 1855-1987 (Box 7-9, 25, OV 24, 28; 2.9 linear feet)
Series 4: Diaries, 1874-1955 (Box 9-10; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 5: Writings, 1888-1989 (Box 10-11, 25; 1.1 linear foot)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1867-1987, 2005 (Box 11-14, 25, OV 24; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1885-1980 (Box 14-16, 18, 20-22, 25, MGP 1, MGP 2, MGP 5, MGP 6; 3.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Artwork, 1895-1935 (Box 18, 20, OV 23; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 9: Scrapbooks, 1895-1963 (Box 18-21, 25; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 10: Estate Records, 1956-2002 (Box 26; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 11: Video Recordings, circa 1980s (Box 26-27; 0.2 linear feet)
Andersen, Hendrik Christian, 1872-1940; Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941; Bennett, Edward H.; Biddle, George, 1885-1973; Blum, Jerome, 1884-1956; Braque, Georges, 1882-1963; Bryant, Louise, 1885-1936; Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; Cole, Walter, b. 1891; Cret, Paul Philippe, 1876-1945; Dismorr, Jessica Stewart, 1885-1939; Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Dreier, Katherine Sophie, 1877-1952; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969; Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-; Halpert, Edith Gregor, 1900-1970; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Heap, Jane; Hecht, Zoltan, 1890-1968; Hélion, Jean, 1904-1987; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-; Léger, Fernand, 1881-1955; Ray, Man, 1890-1976; Raynal, Maurice; Rodin, Auguste, 1840-1917; Sheeler, Charles, 1883-1965; Stella, Joseph, 1877-1946; Sterne, Maurice; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; Storrs, Marguerite Deville Chabrol; Survage, Leopold; Zorach, Marguerite, 1887-1968; Zorach, William, 1887-1966; Artists' studios--France--Paris--Photographs; Diaries; Expatriate artists--France; Painters--France--Paris; Painters--Illinois--Chicago; Photographs; Poems; Portfolios (groups of works); Printmakers--France--Paris; Printmakers--Illinois--Chicago; Prints; Scrapbooks; Sculptors--France--Paris; Sculptors--Illinois--Chicago; Sculpture, Modern--20th century; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Video recordings; World War, 1939-1945--France; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements
- Biographical Material, 1837; 1860-1984; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1, 20, 25, OV 23
  Scope and Contents note
  Scattered biographical material about John Storrs and the Storrs family consist primarily of chronologies and summaries of his career and important life events including a detailed account of family activities from 1939-1945; identification documents such as his birth and death certificates and various passports; records regarding his schooling; award certificates, including an award from the Ordre national de la Légion d'honneur; and membership cards. Family documents include items belonging to David William Storrs, summaries of Storrs family events, and other items pre-dating the birth of John Storrs.
  Also found in this series are two folders of documents, mostly in French, of John and Monique Storrs' activities during World War II. This includes records of Monique's work as a nurse and her participation in the French resistance as well as a few documents regarding their imprisonment by the Gestapo.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Yearbooks and prescription records have not been scanned.
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged by type of materials or subject and items are arranged chronologically in each folder.
  - Biographical Summaries and Lists, circa 1930s-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical "Outline", 1984 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Chronology, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Birth Certificate for John Storrs, 1885, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Birth Certificate of Monique Storrs, 1918 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - University of Notre Dame High School Records, 1899-1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1903-1905; 3 volumes (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Weekly Schedule, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family Record Book for Storrs and Deville-Chabrol, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Marriage License, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interment Documents for Hannah Bradley Storrs, 1913; 1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Passports and Visas, 1905-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Passport Application for Marguerite Storrs, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eyeglass Prescriptions, 1932, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Certificates, 1837; 1899-1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Oversized items housed in Box 20 and OV 23.
  - Membership Cards, 1905-1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Library Cards, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tickets, 1907-1922; 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Horoscope for John Storrs, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Numerology Analysis, 1920; 1931 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - World War II Documents, 1956; 1953; 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Will and Death Certificate for John Storrs, 1956; 1932 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Design for John Storrs Memorial, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Storrs Family Calling Cards, circa 1880s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Storrs Family Documents, 1860-1943 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - "Etienne Lancelot" Family Tree, circa late-1800s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Oversize Certificates, 1837-1905 (Box 20)
    Scanned with Box 1, Folder 16.
  - Oversize Certificates, 1936; 1905 (Box OV 23)
- Correspondence, 1857-2007; Series 2; 5.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-7, 25
  This series is arranged as 3 subseries.
  2.1: John Storrs Correspondence, 1900-1956
  2.2: Marguerite Storrs Correspondence, 1902-1957
  2.3: Storrs Family Correspondence, 1857-2007
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - John Storrs Correspondence, 1900-1956; 2.1
    John Storrs' extensive correspondence spans over fifty years and documents his personal and professional life. There are extensive letters to his wife Marguerite Storrs, including love letters written before they were married and letters written to her during his visits to the United States. Letters written by Marguerite to John are located series 2.2. John Storrs' love letters to other women, including Yolande de Manziarly, are found within his general correspondence.
    General correspondence primarily consists of Storrs' correspondence with friends, colleagues, art critics and historians, patrons, art organizations, and galleries. Where they exist, Storrs' drafts of outgoing letters are interfiled with letters he received in a chronological arrangement. Storrs was friends with many artists, architects, performers, and writers in both the US and Europe. Among the artists he corresponded with are Berenice Abbott, Hendrick Andersen, George Biddle, Jerome Blum, Arthur Bock, Louis Bouche, Georges Braque, Alexander Calder, Walter Cole, Arthur Davies, Jessica Dismorr, Katherine Dreier, Marcel Duchamp, Leo Friedlander, Marsden Hartley, Jean Helion, Gertrude Lambert, Fernand Leger, Jacques Lipchitz, Man Ray, Richard Recchia, Edwin Scott, Charles Sheeler, Joseph Stella, Maurice Sterne, Alfred Stieglitz, Leopold Survage, Jacques Villon, and William and Marguerite Zorach. Other notable correspondents include architects Edward Bennett, Paul Phillippe Cret, R. Buckminster Fuller, and Alfonso Iannelli; writers and publishers Sherwood Anderson, Louise Bryant, William Bullitt, Max Eastman, Jane Heap, Paul Scott Mowrer, and Gertrude Stein; art critics Phyllis Ackerman, Frank Crowninshield, and Maurice Raynal; art patrons Arthur Aldis, Mildred Bliss, and Charles Worcester; friend and curator Alice Roullier; and dancer Maud Allan. A portion of the general correspondence is in French.
    A small amount of correspondence with galleries, museums, and curators concerns exhibitions and sales of Storrs' artwork. Also found is correspondence concerning his participation in art organizations. Researchers should note a portion of Storrs' business correspondence, especially regarding his major sculpture commissions and his dealings with Downtown Gallery, are found in Series 3: Personal Business Records.
    See Index for a select list of correspondents.
    Index of Correspondents from Series 2.1: John Storrs Correspondence
    Abbott, Berenice, 1921, 1922, undated
    Ackerman, Phyllis, 1924, 1925, 1926, 1927, 1928, undated
    Adams, Cyrus H., 1944
    Adler, Alfred, 1926
    Adler, David, 1939, 1945
    Adrien, Rouet, 1924
    Alby, Leony, undated
    Aldis, Arthur T., 1922, 1923, 1924, 1925, 1926, undated
    Aldis, Graham, 1934
    Allan, Maud, 1907, 1913, 1925, 1928, undated
    American Art Association, 1926, undated
    American Art Bronze Foundry, 1935, 1936
    American Designers Gallery, Inc., 1928
    American Express Company, 1907, 1933
    American Hospital of Paris, 1913
    American Library in Paris, 1945, 1946, 1947
    American Red Cross, 1918
    American Union of Decorative Artists and Craftsmen, 1928, 1929
    American University Union in Europe, 1923
    American Women's Club of Paris, inc., 1932, undated
    Andersen, Mrs. A. O., 1928
    Andersen, Hendrick, 1912, 1913, 1914, 1918
    Anderson, Margaret, 1924
    Anderson, Sherwood, 1917, 1925, undated
    Antheil, George, 1924, 1926, 1927
    A.O. Smith Coporation, 1934
    Apex Smelting Co., 1930
    Arden, Elizabeth, 1935, 1936, undated
    Arens, Egmont, 1919, 1920, 1921
    Arnhem, Edward, 1925
    Art Institute of Chicago, 1920, 1921, 1922, 1925, 1927, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1933, 1934, 1935, 1939, 1940, 1945
    Artists and Writers Dinner Club, 1934
    Arts Club of Chicago, 1920, 1922, 1927, 1928, 1932, 1934, 1937
    Artwork, 1924
    Ateliers D'Art du Clos De Joye, 1955
    B., Simone, 1924, 1926, 1928, undated
    Babcock, Ella, 1912, undated
    Babcock, James L., 1904, 1905, 1906, 1907, 1908, 1909, 1910, undated
    Bailey, C. Foster, 1928
    Ballard, George S., 1935
    Barbarin, Georges, 1942
    Barbier, H., 1925
    Barbusse, Leevri, 1919
    Barrett, Ida C., 1939
    Bartholomew, Marshall, 1937
    Bartlett, Paul W., 1914
    Beach, John & Lucy, 1909, 1911, 1912, 1913, 1914, 1916, 1918, 1919, 1923, 1925, 1926, 1945, undated
    Benard, Maddy, undated
    Benington, Walter, 1918
    Benjamin, Elizabeth, undated
    Bennett, Edward H., 1934, 1935, 1937, 1938, 1940, 1944, 1945, 1948, 1951
    Berger, Paul, 1920
    Berlin Photographic Company, 1915
    Biddle, George, 1923, 1924, 1925, 1946, undated
    Biddle, Katherine Garrison, 1928
    Jane Biddle, 1925, 1926
    Birdsall, Lucy Storrs, 1950, undated
    Birnbaum, Martin, 1916
    Blanquet-Pernot, Mrs., 1928
    Bliss, Mildred, 1929, 1948, undated
    Blinstrub, Ben, 1937, 1945
    Blum, Frank, 1929
    Blum, Jerome, 1907, undated
    Bock, Arthur, 1906
    Bon, Jacques, 1923
    Booz, Helen, 1946, 1947, undated
    Bonney, M. Therese, 1926
    Bosley, Frederick A., 1907, 1909, undated
    Bouche, G. Louis (Folsom Galleries), 1920, 1921, undated
    Boulenger, Jacques, 1942
    Boyce, Sydney, 1911
    Boyd, Jim, 1906
    Bragdon, Marston S., 1914
    Brandt, Edgar, 1926
    Braque, G., 1939, 1955
    Breck, George W., 1907
    Bretano's, 1913
    Brewster, Kate Lancaster, 1929, undated
    Brewster, Walter, 1928
    Brooklyn Museums, 1930, 1934
    Brorby, Melvin, 1924
    Brown, A. Spenser, 1907, 1912, 1913, 1914, undated
    Brown, Slater, 1921
    Brummer, Joseph, 1928, 1929, 1930
    Bryant, Louise, 1917, 1918, 1920, 1922, 1923, 1924, 1925, 1929, 1930, undated
    Bucher, Jeanne, 1937, undated
    Bulliet, C. J., 1949
    Bullitt, Orville H., undated
    Bullitt, William C., 1937, 1939, 1940, undated
    Butcher, Fanny, 1931
    Byrne, Barry, 1928, 1930
    Caffery, Jefferson, 1944, 1945
    Cahiers de L'Etoile, 1929
    Calder, Alexander (Illustrated Letter), 1932, 1935
    California Museum of Art, Palace of the Legion of Honor, 1923, 1924, 1933
    Calton, Constance, 1948
    Campbell, Elisa, undated
    Carnegie Institute, 1938
    Caro-Delvaille, Aline, 1923
    Carpenter, Genevieve, 1928, 1929
    Carpenter, Rue, 1927
    Cartarin, A., 1924
    Carter, Helen B., 1921, 1922
    Cecile, Paul, 1929
    Centre Immobilier et Forestier, 1923
    Chambers, Christine, undated
    Chandler, George M., 1921
    Chapman, C., 1912, undated
    Charles Fiore Nurseries, 1930
    Charpentier, Jean, 1926
    Chase Bank, 1946
    Cheney, Sheldon (Theatre Arts Magazine), 1921
    Chicago Academy of Fine Arts, 1933, 1934, 1935
    Chicago Daily News, 1918
    Chicago Sculptors Association, 1935, 1936
    Chicago Society of Etchers, 1916, 1918
    Child, Paul Cushing & Julia, 1929, 1950
    Childs, Newell, 1940, 1945, undated
    Christy, Bill, 1946
    Chrysler, Walter P., 1939
    Civil Affairs Office, Orleans, France, 1944
    Clarke, Dora, undated
    Cliff Dwellers, 1928
    Cline, Jared, 1927, 1928
    Clow, Isabelle, 1927, 1928
    Cohalan, Daniel, 1930
    Colbert, F. Overton, 1933
    Cole, Timothy, 1917
    Cole, Walter, 1907, 1908, 1909, 1910, 1911, 1912, 1919, undated
    Coleville, Ruth, 1912
    College of St. Scholastica, 1939
    Combes Favard, Berthe des, 1921, undated
    Compagnie Generale Transatlantique, 1916, 1923, 1927
    Commission de la Renaissance d'Orleans, 1945
    Consulate-General of the United States of America, 1914
    Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1935
    Coules, Edith V., 1926, undated
    Cowles, Genevieve, 1927
    Crane, Jacob, 1933
    Creative Art, 1928
    Cret, Paul Philippe & Marguerite, 1925, 1926, 1930, 1945, undated
    Cross, Louise, 1932
    Crowninshield, Frank, 1929
    Cummings, Nathan, 1955, 1956
    Cummings, Walter, undated
    Cunningham, John, 1933, 1938, 1955
    Cuttoli, Marie, undated
    Dallies, Jeanne, 1917
    Dashiell, Juliet A., 1905, 1906, 1907
    Davies, Arthur, 1923